Byzantine Institute, Inc. Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection. The Byzantine Institute and Dumbarton Oaks Fieldwork Records and Papers, ca. late 1920s-2000s: Finding Aid
Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives, Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection
- Fieldwork Papers, 1920s -2000s, MS.BZ.004-02; 46 boxes including 494 folders; 29 boxes including 29 photo albums; 20+ oversize files; 26 boxes of backlog materials; 2 boxes including 14 folders of accumulated research materials by ICFA staff
  - Fieldwork Notebooks and Research Notes, ca. 1929-1970s, MS.BZ.004-02-01; 30 boxes containing 299 folders
    - Fieldwork Notebooks, Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii, Istanbul, Turkey, 1940-1954, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03; 3 boxes 31 folders
      - Phoutrides, Evan, "Notes on the Work at the Church of St. Savior in the Chora during the 1948 Season", 1948, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-215; 1 folder
        Includes a detailed account of work conducted in Kariye Camii and notes about the John panel in Hagia Sophia
        Evan Phoutrides was a Byzantine Institute field worker, ca. 1948
        Phoutrides, Evan
      - Caruana, Nicholas, "Kahriye Camisi", June 16, 1949 - November 10, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-216; 1 folder
        Descriptions of work conducted at bay 1 on the second lunette panel at Kariye Camii
      - Cidrof, Dinco, "Kariye Camisi", June 20, 1949 - November 5, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-217; 1 folder
        The author states in French that he had to end his work because he was called for military service
        Cidrof Dinco was a Byzantine Institute field worker at Kariye Camii in 1949
        Dinco, Cidrof
      - Durnoff, Antonyo, "Kahriye Camisi", June 20, 1949 - September 4, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-218; 1 folder
        The author states in Turkish that sometime in August 1949, a few key individuals from the American and Turkish consulate came to visit Kariye Camii.
      - Hawkins, Ernest, "Diary: Confidential", May 29, 1949 - November 21, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-219; 1 folder
        Refers to Iskender's color photography of Kariye Camii on November 14, 1949. Also on the back, it includes a list of color photographs taken by Iskender in 1949. On the back of the cover, a note states: "E. Hawkins 1949 Diary was taken by Prof. Paul A. Underwood Aug. 4th 1950"
      - James, Michael, "Panel No. 7", June 28, 1949 - September 30, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-220; 1 folder
        Includes descriptions of work conducted at the "Panel No. 7" (exonarthex, west wall, second bay from north). The author also describes the "Whittemore Method" of conservation: "The Whittemore Method of conservation is right. It is an impersonal method. The mosaic is left as it is found but intact. The spirit of the mosaic is never tampered with; for nothing is added, no cubes rearranged; no attempt is [?] to replace. Here, by the grace of Thomas Whittemore, the Byzantine reveals himself."
        Michael James was a Byzantine Institute field worker
        James, Michael
      - Makridis, Yani, "Notes", June 16, 1949 - October 10, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-221; 1 folder
        Descriptions of work conducted on panel no. 3 (exonarthex, west wall, first bay from north)
        Yani Makridis was a Byzantine Institute field worker, ca. 1949-1960s. Assisted in the conservation work in Istanbul, and carried out the cleaning, restoring and photographing of frescoes in Asinou, Koutsovendis, Monagri, and Paphos in Cyprus.
        Makridis, Yani
      - Mercevier, Jean, "Kahriye Camisi, June 16, 1949 - October 28, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-222; 1 folder
        Descriptions of work conducted at table no. 3 and saints in the soffit
        Jean Mercevier was a Byzantine Institute field worker at Kariye Camii from ca. 1949-1959.
        Mercevier, Jean
      - Tsaousis, Kostantinos, "Kahriye Camisi", June 15, 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-223; 1 folder; The end date is not known.
        Constantine Tsaousis was an art conservator who helped restore frescoes in Hagia Sophia. He worked with Carroll Wales at Oliver Brothers Restoration in Boston, Massachusetts.
        Tsaousis, Constantine
      - Underwood, Paul A. (possibly), "Hagia Sophia: Notes on Mosaics in [the south west room]", 1949, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-224; 1 folder
      - Hawkins, Ernest (possibly), "Notes on Work in Istanbul", July 27, 1950 - October 1950, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-225; 1 folder
        Descriptions of work conducted in Hagia Sophia and Kariye Camii. Also contains notes documenting the vandalism of gold mosaic cubes at Hagia Sophia and a list of names of visitors to Hagia Sophia.
      - Cyril Mango's notes on Kariye Camii, July 1954, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-226; 1 folder
      - Underwood, Paul A., Hagia Sophia: West wall of nave, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-227; 1 folder
      - Underwood, Paul A., Deësis Mosaic: Hagia Sophia [South] Gallery, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-03-228; 1 folder
    - Photograph Logs, Hagia Sophia, 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04; 2 boxes including 14 folders
      For related photographs and photo albums, see Subgroup 2, Series 2, Subseries 1-4.
      - "Catalogue of Photographs", 1932-1934, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-229; 1 folder
      - "LIST OF PHOTOGRAPHS TAKEN IN ST. SOPHIA AT ISTANBUL IN 1933 BY MR. WHITTEMORE", 1933, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-230; 1 folder; A note below the title states: "not correct/ P. Iskender"
      - "Rough Records of Photographs Taken", Late 1934 - 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-231; 1 folder
      - "LIST OF PHOTOGRAPHS TAKEN IN ST. SOPHIA AT ISTANBUL", 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-232; 1 folder
      - Gregory, Richard A., "Rough Tabulation Book of Photographs", May 9, 1935 - November 11, 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-233; 1 folder
      - Gregory, Richard A., "(Rough) List of Photographs", June 17, 1936 - December 4, 1936, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-234; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "Rough Diary of Photos taken at St. Sophia Museum"
        Descriptions of work conducted on the apse and south gallery panels. Also includes a list of photography taken on November 19, 1936.
      - Gregory, Richard A., "LIST OF PHOTOGRAPHS", June 17, 1936 - 1938, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-235; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "Tabulation of Photographs taken at St. Sophia Museum"
        Includes lists and descriptions of Fossati repairs, brickwork, mortar, inscriptions, and conditions of light from the John and Zoe panels, south gallery, apse, and southwest vestibule
      - Gregory, Richard A., "List of Photos taken at St. Sophia", June 18, 1937 - November 22, 1937, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-236; 1 folder
        Richard A. Gregory signed the notebook on November 26, 1937.
      - Gregory, Richard A., "List of Photographs", June 18, 1937 - November 22, 1937, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-237; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "LIST OF PHOTOGRAPHS TAKEN AT ST. SOPHIA MUSEUM"
        Richard A. Gregory signed the notebook on November 23, 1937.
      - Gregory, Richard A., "Lists of Photographs Taken at St. Sophia", June 7, 1938 - August 31, 1938, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-238; 1 folder
      - Gregory, Richard A., "Working lists of photographs taken at St. Sophia", June 7, 1938 - August 31, 1938, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-239; 1 folder
      - Hawkins, Ernest, "PHOTOGRAPHS", May 31, 1939 - October 21, 1939, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-240; 1 folder
      - Hawkins, Ernest, "Photographs: Record of Photographs Taken in the Season of 1940", June 22, 1940 - December 4, 1940, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-241; 1 folder
      - Hawkins, Ernest, "Moving Pictures in Colour: Record of moving pictures in colour taken during the season 1940 of work on the mosaics of Aya Sophia", July 25, 1940 - December 3, 1940, MS.BZ.004-02-01-04-242; 1 folder
    - Other Fieldwork Projects in Turkey, 1940s -1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05; 2 boxes including 13 folders
      Related to other fieldwork projects in Turkey, including Fatih Camii, Fethiye Camii, Fenari Isa Camii (Monastery of Lips), and Kalenderhane Camii, among others. Also includes covers from Byzantine Institute fieldwork notebooks.
      - Excavation plans and drawings for Fatih Camii, 1949-1950, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-243; 1 folder
        Includes a sketch of the area of Saraçhane and Kavafhane and an excavation plan for the south side of Fatih Camii, October 18, 1949. Also includes a letter from Nezih Firatli to Paul Underwood, November 1, 1950.
      - Ground plan drawing of Fatih Camii, No Date, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-244; 1 folder
      - Plans and drawings of mosaics for Fethiye Camii, April 1958 - June 1962, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-245; 1 folder
      - Beslemez, Sinasi, "Kursunlu Monastery: drawings from an architectural survey", 1959, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-246; 1 folder
        Şinasi Beşlemez was the creator of drawings of Kursunlu Monastery, 1959.
        Beşlemez, Şinasi
      - Underwood, Paul A., "Mosaics of Fethiye Camii", 1961, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-247; 1 folder
      - "Summary of work carried out in Cyprus in the Spring of 1963 by the Dumbarton Oaks Centre for Byzantine Studies (Harvard University) in Collaboration with the Cyprus Department of Antiquities", 1963, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-248; 1 folder
        Relates to work conducted in St. Neophytos. Also includes a report on "Byzantine Mosaics in Cyprus New Conservation Work", which includes work conducted at Panagia Kanakaria and Panagia tis Kyras
      - Maps and photographs of frescoes at Fenari Isa Camii (Monastery of Lips), from Cyril Mango, ca. early 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-249; 1 folder; Materials were possibly created during the season of 1963 and 1964.
        For more information, see 'Dumbarton Oaks Papers' nos. 18 (1964) and 22 (1968).
      - Essay entitled "Fenari Isa Sculptures", undated [1963-1964], MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-250; 1 folder; The essay was possibly written by Ernest Hawkins. It is also possible that the materials in this folder were created between 1963 and 1964.
      - "Notes on 'survey' of location of Niche with fresco near Yidi Kuli", undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-251; 1 folder; Refers to the transfer and conservation of one fresco at Etyemez between 1957 and 1958, also described as “Samatya” fresco
      - Site plans for Kalenderhane, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-252; 1 folder
      - Original covers from the Byzantine Institute fieldwork notebooks, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-05-253/254/255; 1 box 3 folders
    - Bargala Excavations, Republic of Macedonia (Former Yugoslavia): Research Notes, 1968-1970s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06; 1 box including 8 folders
      - Research proposal from Lyman H. Legters to the Program Director of the Foreign Currency Program at the Smithsonian Institute, submission date 1968 - 1969, 1968 -1969, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-256; 1 folder
        The project title was "Byzanto-Slavic Culture of Medieval Bargala" and the proposed project schedule was from summer 1969 to summer 1973.
        Lyman H. Legters is an American scholar, Professor of Slavic Studies and Associate Director of the Far Eastern and Russian Institute at the University of Washington.
        Legters, Lyman H., 1928-
      - Drawings of St. George, section looking North, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-257; 1 folder
        Archival history
        Accession numbers: Ia.2.6.6a-Ia.2.6.6d
        In ICFA cold storage, four (4) 35mm negatives of St. George (site plan) and regional maps may relate to the materials in this folder.
      - "GRID COORDINATE SYSTEM", August 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-258; 1 folder
      - "Provisional Inventory [and] Suggested Inventory System for Bargala Excavations", 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-259; 1 folder
      - Research proposal from Cyril Mango, 1970s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-260; 1 folder
        The project was a collaboration with the Skopje Archaeological Museum. The project title was "Medieval Bargala" and the proposed project schedule was from 1970 to 1975.
      - Aleksova, Blaga and Cyril Mango, "BARGALA: A PRELIMINARY REPORT", ca. 1970s, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-261; 1 folder
      - Architectural drawings of columns, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-262; 1 folder
        For related materials, see oversize drawings BF.F.1993.F994-.F1000: Inventory Lists\ Inventory Drawing Maps\BI-DO Fieldwork Drawings\EmbARK records #170-176.
      - Triangulations, No Date, MS.BZ.004-02-01-06-263; 1 folder
    - Bargala Excavations, Republic of Macedonia (Former Yugoslavia): Fieldwork Notebooks, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07; 1 box including 8 folders
      - Boyd, Sue, "Bargala B-3 St. George", July 29, 1970 - August 7, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-264; 1 folder
        Susan A. Boyd was the curator of the Photographs Collection at Dumbarton Oaks (now the Image Collections and Fieldwork Archives), ca. 1960s - 1970s. Boyd later became the Curator of the Byzantine Collection, 1979 - 2004. She assisted Dumbarton Oaks sponsored field work in Cyprus, and was an American team member of a joint Yugoslav-American expedition (by the Archaeological Museum of Skopje and Dumbarton Oaks) conducting excavations at Bargala (now known as Goren Kozjak), in eastern Macedonia, 1969-1970
        Boyd, Susan A.
      - Chodoff, David, "Bargala", July 21, 1970 - August 21, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-265; 1 folder
        David Chodoff was an American team member and trench supervisor of a joint Yugoslav-American expedition (by the Archaeological Museum of Skopje and Dumbarton Oaks) conducting excavations at Bargala (now known as Goren Kozjak), in eastern Macedonia, 1970
        Chodoff, David
      - Drewer, Louis, "BARGALA NORTHEAST AREA", July 24, 1970 - August 17, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-266; 1 folder
        Louis Drewer is a Coptic art specialist. American team member and trench supervisor of a joint Yugoslav-American expedition (by the Archaeological Museum of Skopje and Dumbarton Oaks) conducting excavations at Bargala (now known as Goren Kozjak), in eastern Macedonia, 1970
        Drewer, Louis
      - Mango, Cyril, "Bargala 1970", July 19, 1970 - August 17, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-267; 1 folder
      - Megaw, Arthur Huber Stanley, "Bargala 1970", July 22, 1970 - July 30,1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-268; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "Bargala Excavations 1970"
      - Rosser, John, "Bargala Excavations 1970", July 16, 1970 - August 14, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-269; 1 folder
        John Rosser is an American Byzantinist and author of the Historical Dictionary of Byzantium. Rosser was an American team member and trench supervisor of a joint Yugoslav-American expedition (by the Archaeological Museum of Skopje and Dumbarton Oaks) conducting excavations at Bargala (now known as Goren Kozjak), in eastern Macedonia, 1970
        Rosser, John, 1942-
      - Sevcenko, Ihor, "Bargala 1970", July 9, 1970 - August 3, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-270; 1 folder
      - "1970 PHOTO BOOK", July 15, 1970 - August 27, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-07-271; 1 folder
        Title from first page: "Bargala 1970 PHOTOGRAPHIC RECORD BOOK"
    - Bargala Excavations, Wax Imprints of Graffiti, July 15, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08; 3 boxes including 24 folders of wax imprints; Descriptions for items in this subseries are derived from Jeff Schlosberg's 1981-1982 inventory. For more information, consult the black binder in Folder 2 of the Addendum.
      Wax imprints are very fragile, please handle with care.
      - Greek inscription (official), Inv #158, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-272; 1 folder
        Wax imprints are very fragile, please handle with care
      - Horse graffito, Inv #B232, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-273; 1 folder
      - Roundel graffito, Inv #B233, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-274; 1 folder
      - Graffito of lines, Inv #B234, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-275; 1 folder
      - Half roundel graffito, Inv #B235, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-276; 1 folder
      - Graffito of line decorations, Inv #B236, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-277; 1 folder
      - Graffito of decorations, Inv #B237, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-278; 1 folder
      - Greek inscription graffito, Inv #B238, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-279; 1 folder
      - Graffito of a peacock or hen (?), Inv #239, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-280; 1 folder
      - Graffito of doodles, Inv #B240, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-281; 1 folder
      - Graffito of doodles, Inv #B241, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-282; 1 folder
      - Graffito of crisscrossed lines, Inv #B242, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-283; 1 folder
      - Graffito of crisscrossed lines, Inv #B243, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-284; 1 folder
      - Graffito of inscriptions, July 15, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-285; 1 folder
      - Inscribed cross and other symbols (possibly an alpha), July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-286; 1 folder
      - South wall (room 2), Greek inscription (official), July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-287; 1 folder
      - South wall (room 2), inscribed triangle, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-288; 1 folder; Wax imprints are very fragile, please handle with care.
      - North wall (room 3), possibly Greek inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-289; 1 folder
      - North wall (room 3), possibly Greek inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-290; 1 folder
      - North wall (room 3), possibly Greek inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-291; 1 folder
      - North wall (room 3), July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-292; 1 folder
      - West wall (room 3), possibly Greek inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-293; 1 folder
      - Inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-294; 1 folder
      - Graffiti of Greek inscriptions, July 21, 1970 - July 22, 1970, MS.BZ.004-02-01-08-295; 1 folder; Wax imprints are very fragile, please handle with care.
    - Project Materials: Church of Panagia Amasgou at Monagri, Cyprus and Dibsi Faraj Excavations, Syria, 1972-1973, MS.BZ.004-02-01-09; 1 box containing 4 folders
      Materials relating to fieldwork projects at the Church of Panagia Amasgou at Monagri, Cyprus and at Dibsi Faraj, Syria
      - Photograph logbook (black and white and colour), Church of Panagia Amasgou at Monagri, July - August 1972, MS.BZ.004-02-01-09-296; 1 folder
      - "Coin hoard photography", Church of Panagia Amasgou at Monagri, September 1972, MS.BZ.004-02-01-09-297; 1 folder
      - Binder of research notes, Church of Panagia Amasgou at Monagri, undated, MS.BZ.004-02-01-09-298; 1 folder
      - Work journal and seasonal reports, Dibsi Faraj, Syria, May 1972 - November 1973, MS.BZ.004-02-01-09-299; 1 folder
  - Fieldwork Reports and Drafts for Publications, 1930s-2000s, MS.BZ.004-02-02; 12 boxes containing 141 folders
    This series contains fieldwork reports, notes, and drafts for publications on Hagia Sophia, Kariye Camii, and Kalenderhane, written between the 1930s and 2000s.
    This series is divided into seven (7) subseries and arranged chronologically by fieldwork order and site (and alphabetical order, if the author’s name exists).
    - Deësis Panel, ca. 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01; 1 box including 8 folders
      Fieldwork reports, notes, and drafts for publications relating to the Deësis mosaic panel in Hagia Sophia.
      - Reports and notes on the Deësis panel, 1930 - 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-300; 1 folder with 3 sets of notes and reports
        - “B. N. E.’s [Boris N. Ermoloff] “Description of colours: John Panel, Deësis, Zoe Panel”, 1930-1935, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-300-001; 30 handwritten pages
        - Kluge, Nicholas, “DEISIS PANEL: SOUTH GALLERY,” October 16, 1935, October 16, 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-300-002; 68 typed, letter-sized pages
        - Kluge, Nicholas, “THIRD REPORT MATERIALS: DEISIS”, October 16, 1935, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-300-003; 64 typed letter-sized pages
      - "FOURTH REPORT DEËSIS PANEL, APPENDIX: TECHNICAL PARTICULARS OF PANEL", 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-301; 1 folder
      - Reports and drafts for the Fourth and Fifth Reports, 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304; 3 folders with 16 items; Fourth Report: The Deësis Panel - Draft was started on November 30, 1949.
        - “THE MOSAICS OF HAGIA SOPHIA AT ISTANBUL: FOURTH REPORT, THE DEËSIS PANEL (Office copy)”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-001; 42 typed letter-sized pages
        - “THE DEËSIS: DESCRIPTION OF THE PANEL ACCORDING TO N. KLUGE’S AND BE’S NOTES”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-002; 14 typed letter-sized pages
        - “A HISTORICAL SURVEY: THE POSITION OF THE DEËSIS”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-003; 17 typed letter-sized pages
        - “THE DEËSIS: ICONOGRAPHICAL STUDY OF THE SUBJECT”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-004; 4 typed letter-sized pages
        - “DEËSIS PANEL: THE COLOURING", 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-005; 4 typed letter-sized pages
        - “THE MARBLE PAVEMENT BEFORE THE DEËSIS PANEL", 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-006; 2 typed letter-sized pages
        - “LIST of selected photographs for Plates for the Deësis Report”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-007; 2 typed letter-sized pages
        - “LIST OF PHOTOGRAPHS for the Deësis Report to be repeated in Istanbul”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-008; 1 typed letter-sized page
        - “Conclusion (Extracted from the draft dated May 31st, 1947)”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-009; 1 typed letter-sized page
        - “Fourth Report, DEËSIS PANEL, APPENDIX: DETAIL OF COLOUR, MEASURE, ETC.”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-010; 34+ typed letter-sized pages
          2 copies of the same document
        - “FIFTH REPORT: THE DEËSIS PANEL”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-011; 18 typed letter-sized pages
        - "CHRIST", 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-012; 4 typed letter-sized pages
        - “FOURTH REPORT: THE DEËSIS PANEL”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-013; 24 typed letter-sized pages
          Draft was started on November 30, 1949.
        - “Work done in 1934 and 1935”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-014; 49 typed letter-sized pages
        - “List of Plates for the IVth Report”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-015; 2 typed letter-sized pages
        - “FIFTH REPORT: THE DEËSIS PANEL”, 1930s-1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-302/303/304-016; 18 typed letter-sized pages
      - "DEËSIS PANEL: EXTRA-MEASUREMENTS by WILLIAM GREGORY", 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-305; 1 folder
      - "FOURTH REPORT: DEËSIS, INTRODUCTION", 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-306; 1 folder
      - Notes, likely for the Fourth Report on the Deësis panel, 1930s - 1940s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-01-307; 1 folder
    - The Study of Light and Techniques, ca. 1930s - 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02; 1 box including 14 folders
      Fieldwork reports, notes, and drafts for publications relating to the study of light in Hagia Sophia and Byzantine mosaic techniques.
      - Notes about the study of light in Hagia Sophia, 1930s - 1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308; 1 folder with 5 groups of notes, reports, and photographs
        - “Report No. 1: Observations in SS”, July and August 1933, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308-001; 2 legal-sized typed pages
        - "[Notes on] November 28", November 28, [1930-1933], MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308-002; 3 handwritten note-sized pages
        - "Notes on the interview with Ismail Efendi (Bayazit Library)", 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308-003; 4 handwritten pages
          English translation of "Efendi" is "Mr"
        - “Mr. Whittemore’s notes on photographs of the light in St. Sophia”, 1930s-1960s, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308-004; 1 typed page
        - “Photographs taken by Mr. Toth in the morning of 29th September 1944 [and] 11th October 1944”, September 29, 1944 - October 11, 1944, MS.BZ.004-02-02-02-308-005; 4 handwritten legal-sized pages